This demo is a quick walkthrough of the research system
behind my current work on first-passage-time distributions in stochastic search,
and why I think this kind of work can become
useful scientific tooling.
The scientific question is simple to state, but rich in
behaviour. If a random walker moves on a ring with
a directed shortcut, how does that geometry reshape the full
distribution of arrival times, not just the mean? I care
about the whole curve: the first peak, the valley between
peaks, the possibility of a second peak, and the parameter
regimes that create those transitions.
What I am proud of here is not only the
mathematics. It is the structure of the project. This is
not a single notebook with a few nice plots. The
repository already separates reports, reusable core code, archives, documentation, and
site outputs. Individual report folders then keep their own code,
figures, data, notes, sections, and outputs. That makes the work
reproducible and easier to extend.
The workflow is equally important. I can define a geometry,
sweep a parameter such as beta or shortcut destination, regenerate
outputs, and compare exact and numerical behaviour inside the same
loop. That means I am not relying on visual intuition
alone. I can turn a question into a clean computational
experiment and then into figures and report-ready conclusions.
One example is the beta sweep. By changing only beta,
I can see how peak timings move, how the bimodal
window changes, and how the entire first-passage curve deforms.
Another example is the destination scan, where I vary only
the shortcut destination and compare exact curves, peak locations, and
second-peak behaviour across cases.
The broader point is that I keep the whole distribution
in view. Instead of collapsing everything to one summary statistic,
I can reason about early and late subpopulations, valley depth,
and shortcut-driven transitions in a much more rigorous way.
Why does that matter beyond theory? Because the same pipeline
can become a decision tool. In BioPath, I want to
use movement models and spatial structure to support precision pest
management, especially questions like trap placement and spatial search design.
So this fellowship would not be a pivot away from
my current work. It would be a way to turn
a rigorous research pipeline into a model-based product for real
scientific and operational decisions.